Guide to the Gil J Wolman Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Gil J Wolman papers
1937-2011
1950-1995
GEN MSS 969
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
37.96
(62 boxes) + 3 broadside, 1 broadside oversize, 3 record album storage
The Gil J Wolman papers consists of correspondence, writings, printed items, artworks, photographs, sound recordings, and other materials by or relating to French artist Gil J Wolman (1929-1995) and his milieu. The collection documents the early Lettrist movement of the 1950s through correspondence, writings of Wolman and others, and materials related to Lettrist films, especially Wolman's Anticoncept (1952) and Isidore Isou's Traité de bave et d'éternité (1951). The collection also documents the creation of Wolman's artist's books, literary works, and sound poetry ("mégapneumie"), as well as his professional career in the Paris art gallery scene from circa 1960 to 1995. Correspondents include Noël Arnaud, Serge Berna, Jean Louis Brau, Guy Debord, François Dufrêne, Isidore Isou, Maurice Lemaître, Dominique
Wolman, Joseph, 1929-1995
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 49 (audiocassette): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
50-52 (record album storage): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Boxes 66-67: Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Charlotte Wolman, Hedy Laure Wolman, and Didier Lecointre-Dominique Drouet on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2012.
Arrangement
Organized into nine series: I. Correspondence, 1946-2004. II. Lettrist Movement Material, 1946-1992. III. Writings, 1950-1995. IV. L'Anticoncept Film Files, 1951-2000. V. Professional Papers, 1952-2008. VI. Artworks, 1965-1992. VII. Audio Recordings, 1965-2010. VIII. Writings about Wolman, 1974-2011. IX. Personal Papers, 1937-1995.
Biographical / Historical
Joseph Wolman (1929-1995), best known by the name Gil J Wolman, was a French artist whose work spanned the visual arts, poetry, sound poetry, and filmmaking. Closely associated with the Lettrist movement, Wolman was among the founding members of the Internationale lettriste.
Born in 1929 in Paris, Wolman spent part of his youth working in wool clothing manufacture, and as a journalist. In 1950, along with Maurice Lemaître, Jean Louis Brau, Serge Berna, and Guy Debord, Wolman joined the young Lettrist movement led by Isidore Isou since 1945. Other figures of significance to the Lettrist movement's evolution from the 1940s to the 1960s include Gabriel Pomerand, François Dufrêne, Jacques Spacagna, and Roberto Altmann.
The years following Wolman's integration to the movement witnessed a period of collaboration among the Lettrists, the production of experimental films, and the publication of several magazines. In 1952, internal disagreements led to the creation of the break-off group Internationale lettriste by Debord, Wolman, Berna, and Brau. This new, radical Lettrism in turn influenced other European avant-garde groups interested in the intersections of art, politics, and society, such as the International Movement for an Imaginist Bauhaus (founded by Asger Jorn, Giuseppe Pinot-Gallizio, and Piero Simondo in 1955 in Italy), the Internationale situationniste (a collective led by Debord created in 1957), and Gruppe Spur (a German collective active from 1957-1965). Excluded from the Internationale lettriste in 1957, Wolman founded the Deuxième internationale lettriste in 1963 with Brau and Dufrêne.
Wolman's contributions to Lettrism are numerous, and include the invention of mégapneumes in the early 1950s (sound poems articulated solely with breath), and the production of content for several publications ( Internationale lettriste, Deuxième internationale lettriste, Potlatch, Ion, etc). Wolman was also involved in Lettrist experimental cinema, not only through his own film L'Anticoncept (1951), but also appearing on the soundtrack of Isou's Traité de bave et d'éternité (1950-51) and Debord's Hurlements en faveur de Sade (1951). Finally, Wolman theorized the technique of "détournement" with Debord in 1956, a technique that would become central to both Debord's Situationist writings, and Wolman's future artistic practices.
From the 1960s onwards, Wolman actively participated in the Paris art gallery scene. In 1963, he invented "art scotch", politically subversive collages of newspaper content extracted from their original pages with translucent adhesive tape. In the 1970s and 1980s, Wolman experimented with photocopy art and the making of artists' books, and developed the "mouvement séparatiste" (the disruptive insertion of blank spaces in his artworks and texts). In addition to exhibiting in numerous solo and collective shows, Wolman served as editor of the exhibition directory L'Officiel des galeries. Starting circa 1979, Wolman self-published small runs of poetry and art books through his "Éditions inconnues" (Unknown editions).
Wolman met his life partner, artist and writer Charlotte Wolman (née Mandel), at a Lettrist recital in 1958. He passed away on July 3, 1995.
Scope and Contents
The Gil J Wolman Papers consists of correspondence, writings, printed material, artworks, photographs, audio recordings, and other materials by or relating to French artist Gil J Wolman (1929-1995) and his milieu. The collection documents the early Lettrist movement through correspondence, writings of Wolman and others, and material related to Lettrist films, especially Wolman's L'Anticoncept and Isidore Isou's Traité de bave et d'éternité. Correspondents include Noël Arnaud, Serge Berna, Jean Louis Brau, Guy Debord, François Dufrêne, Isidore Isou, Maurice Lemaître, Dominique Meens, and others. Of note are preparatory material for the Internationale lettriste periodical and mégapneumie notations, as well as Lettrist poems, screenplays, and theoretical texts in manuscript or typescript authored and annotated by the movement's leading figures, especially by Debord, Isou, Brau, and Dufrêne. The collection also holds the unpublished last pages of Guy Debord's "Manifeste pour une construction des situations" (1953).
Additionally, the collection documents Wolman's literary works, sound poetry, and professional career in the Paris gallery scene. Drafts, printing tests, and visuals for Wolman's artists' books created from the mid-1970s to the early 1990s constitute a large part of the collection, and feature, among others, Dühring, Dühring (1979), L'homme séparé (1979), Wolman résumé des chapitres précédents (1981), Les inhumations: suivi de Peinture dépeinte (1995). Evidence of Wolman's artistic production include exhibition catalogs, invitation cards, administrative records, and a small number of original artworks, including an art scotch canvas and prints.
Anticoncept (Motion picture); Traité de bave et d'éternité (Motion picture); Artists -- France -- 20th Century; Authors, French -- 20th Century -- Archives; Experimental films -- France; French literature -- 20th Century; Lettrism -- France; Lettrism in motion pictures; Artists' books (books) -- France -- 20th Century; Audiovisual materials; Lettrist literature -- France -- Paris -- 20th Century; Photographs; Screenplays; Screen prints; Sound recordings; Arnaud, Noël; Berna, Serge; Brau, Jean Louis; Debord, Guy, 1931-1994; Dufrêne, François, 1930-1982; Isou, Isidore; Lemaître, Maurice, 1926-; Meens, Dominique; Wolman, Joseph, 1929-1995; Internationale lettriste; Internationale situationniste
- Correspondence, 1946-2004; Series I; 2.1; (5 boxes)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Box 66: Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
  Related Materials
  Correspondence on the preparation of exhibitions can also be found among administrative documents in Series V. Professional Papers. Mail art can also be found in Series VI. Artworks, with other items gathered by Wolman as source material for collages and copy art.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I. comprises incoming correspondence, largely of a professional nature, from artists, writers, gallery administrators, book sellers, scholars, and friends. Rich correspondence from Guy Debord, Maurice Lemaître, Serge Berna, and Jean Louis Brau offers a view into the Lettrist movement of the early 1950s: the internal politics of their membership, their relations with the French authorities, the creation of their magazines, and their theories about art, politics, and society. A smaller number of letters dating from the 1960s-1970s by other significant avant-garde figures in Wolman's milieu is also extant, including from Isidore Isou, Henri Chopin, Noël Arnaud, François Dufrêne, and Roberto Altmann. Letters from administrators of cultural institutions in Europe and the United States discuss the planning of exhibitions or film screenings featuring works by Wolman. Also of note is extensive correspondence from poet and author Dominique Meens accompanied by drafts of his writings.
  - "A" general, 1965-1991 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Aeschbacher, Arthur, 1982-1993 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Altmann, Roberto, 1964-1972 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Amann, [Herman?], 1974-1986 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    With joint letters from France Amann.
  - Arnaud, Noël, 1964-1992 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Letters include discussion of the creation of the poetry and art magazine Dragée haute (1964), and collaborative exhibitions.
  - Arnaud, Noël. Third party correspondence, 1993- (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Photocopies of letters to Jacques Bens, accompanied by no. 1-5 of the literary serial Nos classiques vivants, each consisting of one printed page.
  - Association internationale de la lettre et du signe, 1977-1979 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Aubertin, Bernard, 1965-1974 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Also includes joint letters from Bernard and Denise A. Aubertin.
  - Aubertin, Denise A., 1976-1995 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "B" general, 1952-1992 (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
  - Bar-Nir, Bernard, 1982-1993 (Box 1, Folder 12-13)
    Israeli journalist writing to Wolman about living conditions in Jerusalem and personal matters.
  - Bauduin, 1977-1994 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Includes mail art.
  - Béguin, Monique, 1977-1979 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Letters concerning the planning of the festival Artistes en liberté dans le Perche, in Bellême, France.
    See also: Ville de Bellême, Artiste en liberté dans le Perche participant dossier, Series V., Box 39, Folder 545.
  - Berlé, Pierre-Joël, 1953- (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Letter, returned by prison administration, from Wolman to fellow lettrist "Pierre Berlé dit Joell", discussing Wolman's interrogation and deposition about Berlé.
    See also: Mension, Jean-Michel, Box 4, Folder 100, for an addendum by Berlé.
  - Berna, Serge, 1953-1954 (Box 1, Folder 17-18)
    Letters, some censored, sent by Berna from jail featuring discussions of the Lettrist movement.
  - Bernstein, Michèle, 1985-1991 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Berreby, Gérard, 1983-1994 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Bertini, Gianni, 1989-1993 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Bisson-Millet, Paule-Léon, 1985-1989 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Bodson, Guy, 1983- (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Brau, Jean Louis, 1952-1961, and later (Box 1, Folder 24-26)
    Includes a long letter circa 1953 explaining his reasons for leaving the Internationale lettriste, a letter from Algeria dated 1953 April 17, and an undated letter from Long Hai, Vietnam, circa the mid-1950s discussing war, Marxism, and Isidore Isou.
  - Brown, Jean, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - "C" general, 1969-1994 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Centre national de la cinématographie, 1951-1952 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    Incoming and outgoing letters regarding censorship and screening rights for Wolman's film L'Anticoncept.
    See also: Series IV. L'Anticoncept Film Files, Certificate from the Centre national de la cinématographie, Box 37, Folder 503.
  - Chopin, Henri, 1965-1983 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Cinedoc, 1994-1995 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Cinémathèque de Belgique, 1952- (Box 2, Folder 32)
    Regarding a screening of Isidore Isou's Traité de bave et d'éternité.
  - Clavel, Claude, 1977-1991 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    Contains three invitation cards and one painted mail art postcard.
  - Constant, Bernard, 1983 and undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Corfou, Michel, 1980-1984 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    Includes mail art (1980), and a proposal for exchanging artworks accompanied by Corfou's curriculum vitae (1984).
  - Costa, Mario, 1977-1983 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    Accompanied by a photocopy of Costa's article "Arte e spontaneità rivoluzionaria" (1974).
  - Criton, Jean, 1981-1993 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Curtay, Jean-Paul, 1978-1985 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - "D" general, 1976-1985 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Dassonville, Gustave Arthur, 1976 and undated (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Debord, Guy, 1952-1957 (Box 2, Folder 41-46)
    Letters, most undated, discussing the theories and politics of the Lettrist movement, including Debord's disagreements with Isidore Isou and with other members, the preparation of the Lettrist magazines Potlatch and Internationale lettriste, and a report of an evening of "dérive". The correspondence is accompanied by two photographs; three autograph texts ("Réponse à une enquête du groupe surréaliste belge: Quel sens donnez-vous au mot poésie?", "Circonstances de l'esprit nouveau", and "Internationale lettriste no. 2 Manifeste"); and an autograph list of mailing addresses for Potlatch.
    - Oversize letter, circa 1955 (Box 56 (Oversize), Folder 735)
  - Decelle, Eric, 1974-1994 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    Regarding Decelle's acquisitions of Wolman's artworks.
  - Delcour, Bertrand, 1994- (Box 2, Folder 48)
    Entreprise 7891, no. 1 (1987) is enclosed.
  - Devaux, Frédèrique, 1984-1991 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Duchêne, Gérard, undated (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Dufrêne, François, 1959-1981 (Box 2, Folder 51-52)
    Consists largely of postcards signed by Dufrêne and his family [initials "f.g.f.n."].
  - Dufrêne, François. Third-party correspondence, 1978- (Box 2, Folder 53)
    Contains photocopies of letters exchanged between Dufrêne, Henri Chopin, and Arrigo Lora-Totino debating statements about Lettrist and Ultra-Lettrist artists made by Lora-Totino in the anthology of sound poetry Futura: poesia sonora (Milano: Cramps Records, 1978).
  - "E" general, 1989-1992 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - "F" general, 1974-1982 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Feugereux, Jean, 1964- (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Fillon, Jacques H., 1954-1958 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Forest, Fred, 1977-1989 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Franco, Cérès, undated (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - "G" general, 1974-1993 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Galerie Atlante / Galerie Salammbo, 1986-1988 (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - Galerie Lara Vincy, 1977-1994 (Box 3, Folder 62)
  - Galerie de Paris, undated (Box 3, Folder 63)
    - Fragile originals on thermal paper (Box 66, Folder 793)
  - Galerie Spiess (Paris, France), 1984-1989 (Box 3, Folder 64)
    See also Spiess, Jacques. Box 5, Folder 120-121.
  - Galleria Antiope / Centro d'arte contemporanea Antiope, 1977-1979 (Box 3, Folder 65)
  - Gallimard (firm), 1983- (Box 3, Folder 66)
  - Gallizio, Piergiorgio, 1956-1989 (Box 3, Folder 67)
  - Gauvin, Alain, 1984-1991 (Box 3, Folder 68)
  - Glantz, Suzanne (née Dortort), circa 1946-1950 (Box 3, Folder 69)
    Contains one postcard and telegraph receipts.
  - Grumel, Pierre, 1950-1955 (Box 3, Folder 70)
  - "H" general, 1981-1995 (Box 3, Folder 71)
    - Fragile letter on thermal paper, 1993 (Box 66, Folder 794)
  - Hopfenblum, Emile, 1950-1974 (Box 3, Folder 72)
  - [Hops?], Emile, 1991-1994 (Box 3, Folder 73)
  - Institute of Contemporary Art (Boston, Mass.), 1989- (Box 3, Folder 74)
    Regarding the showing of L'Anticoncept organized by the ICA and the recording of the audience's reactions to the film, with loan invoice enclosed.
  - Isou, Isidore, 1961-1991 (Box 3, Folder 75)
    Letters and invitations, largely regarding the Biennale de Paris of 1963 and the exhibition La lettre et le signe dans la peinture contemporaine (Galerie Valerie Schmidt, 1963).
  - "J" general, 1972-1993 (Box 3, Folder 76)
  - Jeannet, Jacques, 1976-1978 (Box 3, Folder 77)
  - Jessemin, Aude, 1991-1993 (Box 3, Folder 78)
    Contains holiday cards.
    See also: Spacagna, Jacques, Box 5, Folder 119, for joint letters sent by Jessemin and Spacagna.
  - Kerg, Théo, undated (Box 3, Folder 79)
  - Koskas, George, undated (Box 3, Folder 80)
  - "L" general, 1980-1986 (Box 3, Folder 81)
  - Lamy, circa 1971-1980 (Box 3, Folder 82-83)
  - Lemaître, Maurice, 1961-1969 (Box 3, Folder 84-88)
    Contains typed circular letters sent to members of Lemaître's Lettrist circle discussing the publications of Lettrist magazines, particularly Nouvelle génération, collaborative exhibitions, disagreements with Isou, and the internal politics of the Lettrist movement. Most letters are by Lemaître, but the grouping also includes a small number of responses from Jean Louis Brau, Jacques Spacagna, and Pierre Descamps.
    Also contains letters addressed to Wolman only. Enclosed in letter postmarked 1962 June 09 are four Ektachrome transparencies of artworks in a gallery.
    See Series II. Lettrist Movement Material, for more documentation on the production of Lettrist magazines.
  - "M" general, 1975-1993 (Box 4, Folder 89)
    Includes mailings of the Les mots perdus literary newsletter (1982).
    - Fragile letter on thermal paper, 1984 (Box 66, Folder 795)
  - Marcus, Greil, 1983-1988 (Box 4, Folder 90)
    Regarding Marcus' scholarly research, and attempt to locate early Lettrist publications.
  - Meens, Dominique, 1978-1995 (Box 4, Folder 91-94)
    Letters, postcards, and envelopes containing drafts from Meens, a poet and writer whose work has featured in Wolman's Éditions inconnues self-publishing label. Poems and texts enclosed in the correspondence include typescripts of "De l'interruption du dire" (1986), "Scolastique de l'être" (1988), and "Porc" (1990); and typed drafts of Ornithologie du promeneur (1991) with corrections by Wolman. Also enclosed is a copy of La trajectoire du figurant by Philippe Joseph Meens (undated).
  - Meens, Dominique. Third-party correspondence, 1995- (Box 4, Folder 95)
    Letters exchanged in March and April 1995 between Meens and Patrick [no last name], forwarded in one envelope to Wolman. The letters discuss extensively Wolman's text Les inhumations.
  - Meens, Dominque. Accompanying writings, 1986, and undated (Box 4, Folder 96-99)
    Contains writings by Meens found with his correspondence, but not enclosed in dated envelopes. Includes "Journées d'un survivant", "Les amuseries du troglodyte", typed drafts of Ornithologie du promeneur (volumes 1-2), Extorsion d'oiseaux (Paris: Éditions inconnues, 1986), and Leçon de choses (Paris: Éditions inconnues, undated).
    - Fragile copies of "Un oiseau d'hiver" and "Moments oisifs" on thermal paper, with manuscript annotations (Box 66, Folder 796)
  - Mension, Jean-Michel, 1953- (Box 4, Folder 100)
    Letter sent to Wolman and Jean Louis Brau at an address in Algeria on paper stamped "Internationale Lettriste", with news of Lettrist members and an addendum by Pierre-Joël Berlé.
  - Mungo-Film, 1989- (Box 4, Folder 101)
    Regarding a request to use footage from L'Anticoncept in a documentary.
  - "N" general, 1977-1982 (Box 4, Folder 102)
  - "O" general, 1983 and undated (Box 4, Folder 103)
  - Obrist, Hans Ulrich, circa 1995 (Box 4, Folder 104)
  - "P" general, 1970-1995 (Box 4, Folder 105)
  - Pillet, Alain-Pierre, 1987- (Box 4, Folder 106)
    Enclosed with a letter dated 1987 July 06 is Pillet's essay "André Breton à Venise: Le plaisir d'une enquête", from the edited volume Du surréalisme et du plaisir (Paris: Librarie José Corti, 1987).
  - "R" general, 1961-1992 (Box 4, Folder 107)
    - Fragile letter on thermal paper, 1992 (Box 66, Folder 797)
  - Rajlich, Jan, 1973-1990 (Box 4, Folder 108)
  - Rivière, Claude, 1975 and undated (Box 4, Folder 109)
  - Rosenthal, Barbara, circa 1952 (Box 5, Folder 110)
    Short note to Wolman and Guy Debord.
  - Rumney, Ralph, 1983-1995 (Box 5, Folder 111)
  - "S" general, 1958-1995 (Box 5, Folder 112)
  - Salvadó, Jacint, 1978-1982 (Box 5, Folder 113)
  - Sanborn, Keith, 1990- (Box 5, Folder 114)
    Incoming and outgoing correspondence regarding filming the audience watching L'Anticoncept during the Exit Art Film Series.
    - Fragile letter on thermal paper, 1990 (Box 66, Folder 798)
  - Sarenco, 1988- (Box 5, Folder 115)
    Letter regarding the creation of a folding screen collection to be photographed and published.
  - Schmidt, Valerie, undated (Box 5, Folder 116)
  - Schwarz, Dieter, 1984-1989 (Box 5, Folder 117)
  - Simondo, Piero, 1984-1990 (Box 5, Folder 118)
  - Spacagna, Jacques, 1964-1979 (Box 5, Folder 119)
  - Spiess, Jacques, 1977-1993 (Box 5, Folder 120-121)
    Contains professional correspondence from Spiess, an art dealer representing Wolman, as well as personal postcards signed by Spiess and Danouchka Bleskine. Also includes a dossier faxed to Wolman in 1993 regarding the exhibition Particulatoire, Galerie L'espace brut.
    For official correspondence by staff of the Galerie Spiess, see also: Galerie Spiess (Paris, France), Box 3, Folder 64.
    - Fragile originals on thermal paper (Box 66, Folder 799)
  - Stern, Nane, 1966-1994 (Box 5, Folder 122)
    - Fragile originals, 1989 (Box 66, Folder 800)
  - "T" general, 1978-1992 (Box 5, Folder 123)
  - Tacussel, Patrick, 1981-1982 (Box 5, Folder 124)
  - Taylor, Simon Watson, circa 1968-1970 (Box 5, Folder 125)
    Largely regarding the organization of an exhibition on Guillaume Apollinaire at the Institute of Contemporary Arts (London, England).
  - "V" general, 1988 and undated (Box 5, Folder 126)
  - Valoch, Jirí, 1969-1977 (Box 5, Folder 127)
  - Villeglé, 1968-1995 (Box 5, Folder 128)
    - Fragile originals on thermal paper (Box 66, Folder 801)
  - Virbel, Jacques, 1983 and undated (Box 5, Folder 129)
  - "W" general, 1951-1973 (Box 5, Folder 130)
  - Wolman, Charlotte. Third-party correspondence, 2003-2004 (Box 5, Folder 131)
    Letters from Nicole Brenez regarding the organization of a program on Gil J Wolman at the Cinémathèque française.
    For correspondence between Charlotte Wolman and Emmanuel Latreille, see Series VIII., "Essays submitted for Defense de mourir ", Box 54, Folder 708.
  - Wolman, Gil J. Outgoing correspondence, 1967-1995 (Box 5, Folder 132)
  - "Y" general, undated (Box 5, Folder 133)
  - Zamire, Anne, 1995 and undated (Box 5, Folder 134)
  - [Unidentified surname], Leopold and Sarah, 1982-1989 (Box 5, Folder 135)
    Personal correspondence regarding their travels
  - First name only, 1959-1986 (Box 5, Folder 136)
  - Unknown correspondents, letters, 1971-1992 (Box 5, Folder 137)
  - Unknown correspondents, orphaned envelopes, 1953-1981 (Box 5, Folder 138)
- Lettrist Movement Material, 1946-1992; 1952-1964; Series II; 1.46; (4 boxes)